hello students and welcome to the lecture
on Information Technology
Basic Concepts
after this lecture
we will be able to learn the falling objectives
understand the concept of information technology
discuss the history of computer technology
explain data storage and databases
describe the data retrieval and data transmission
understand data manipulation
explain the academic
commercial and employment perspective of it
discuss the ethical perspectives of it
let's start with the basic concepts of information
technology
information technology has great influence on
all aspects of life
almost all workplaces and living environments
are being computerized
in order to prepare diploma holders to
work in these environments
it's essential that they are exposed to
various aspects of information technology
such as understanding the concept of information
technology and its scope
operating a computer
use the various tools of Ms Office
using the internet etc
these form the broad competency profile
of diploma holders
information technology is the use of computers to store
and process facts and figures
into a useful organized form
data is the raw material numbers and facts
information is the raw material
organized in a useful way
numbers are data
a telephone book full of numbers information
to emphasize the role of communications
some people use the acronym ICT
which
stands for information and Communication Technology
let's now discuss information technology
the term information technology or it
refers to an entire industry and an actuality
information technology
is the use of computers and software
to manage information
in some companies
this is referred to as management information
services or MIS
or simply as information services is
the
information technology department of a large company
would be responsible for storing information
protecting information
processing the information
transmitting the information as necessary
and later retrieving information
now we will study the history of computer technology
the history has been organized using these
widely recognized generations as mileposts
the mechanical era
1623 to 1945
first generation electronic computers
1937 to 1953
second generation 1954 to 1962
third generation 1963 to 1972
fourth generation 1972 to 1984
fifth generation
1984 to 1990
sixth generation 1990 to date
the mechanical era 1623 to 1945
the idea of using machines to solve
mathematical problems
can be
traced at least as far back as the early 17th century
mathematicians who designed and implemented calculators
that were capable of addition
subtraction
multiplication and division included Wilhelm Shrickard
Lace Pascal and Got Freed Livenets
first generation electronic computers
1937 to 1953
the first programs were written out in machine code
I e programmers
directly wrote down the numbers that corresponded
to the instructions
that they wanted to store in the memory
by the 1950s programmers were using a symbolic notation
known as assembly language
then hand translating the symbolic notation
into machine code
later programs known as assemblers
perform the translation task
second generation 1954 to 1962
during this second generation
many high level programming languages were introduced
including formula translation for Tran 1956
Algal 1958 and Cobalt 1959
important commercial machines of this era
include the IBM 7 0 4 and its successors
the 7 0 9 and 7 0 9 4
the latter introduced I O processors
for better
throughput between I O devices and main memory
the second generation
also saw the first two supercomputers designed
specifically for numeric processing in
scientific applications
third generation 1963 to 1972
the first ICS were based on small scale integration
SSI circuits
which had around 10 devices per circuit or chipped
and evolved to the use of medium scale integrated
MSI circuits which had up to 100 devices per chip
fourth generation 1972 to 1984
the next generation of computer system
saw the use of large scale integration
LSI equals 1,000 devices per chip
and very large scale integration VLSI
100 000 devices per chip
in the construction of computing elements
developments and software included very high
level languages
such as FP Functional Programming
and Prologue Programming in logic
fifth generation
the fifth generation saw the introduction of machines
with hundreds of processors
that could all be working on
different parts of a single program
sixth generation 1990 to date
many of the developments in computer system since 1990
reflect gradual improvements over established systems
and thus
it's hard to claim that they represent a transition
to a new generation
but other developments will prove to be
significant changes
now we will learn about data storage and database
the term data storage can refer to
anything with information recorded on it
using this broad definition
a hardback volume of an encyclopedia
an audio cassette of a pop song
and even a piece of paper with
random words written on it
would all be considered examples
the most popular definition of the term limits it to
only the storage of information on computers and
similar devices
on site storage represents any type of storage device
that's designed to remain with the computer
or at a single location where the computer is housed
offsite data storage is one of the most
recent types of storage
in this type
information is stored away from the computer
at a distant location
database a database is a collection of information
that's organized so that it can be
easily accessed
managed and updated
in one view databases can be classified according to
types of content
bibliographic full text numeric and images
now we will study data retrieval
data retrieval involves the capability to
easily select data
for graphic or attribute editing
updating querying analysis and or display
the ability to retrieve data
is based on the unique structure of the DVMs
and command interfaces are
commonly provided with the software
a backup administrator must be
able to locate the appropriate backup media
and restore the lost data
within an acceptable recovery time objective
or RTO
excessive recovery time translate to lost revenue
and customer relation problems
some of the most
important issues involved in retrieving
data from backups
R setting the RTO
recovering is a process not an event
one of the biggest
challenges with backup planning is the
establishment of a realistic RTO
that will vary depending on the technology in use
and the amount of data to be retrieved
reducing data
another way to accelerate data retrieval
is to reduce the amount of data
that must be backed up in the first place
media management and retention
data retrieval is also affected
by the management and storage of the media itself
tapes and removable hard drives must
be transferred to appropriate storage facilities
routine retrieval testing
most storage organizations
verify the integrity of their backups
by periodically testing the recovery process
for some companies testing is performed
on an ongoing basis as lost user files
are searched and retrieved
now we will study data transmission
data transmission refers
to the movement of data in the form of bits
between two or more digital devices
this transfer of data takes place via some
form of transmission media
for example coaxial cable fiber optics etc
types of data transmission
parallel transmission
in parallel transmission
all the bits of data are transmitted simultaneously
on separate communication lines
parallel transmission is used for
short distance communication
serial transmission
in serial transmission
the various bits of data are transmitted serially
one after the other
it requires only one communication line
rather than end lines
to transmit data from center to receiver
there are two types of cereal transmission
synchronous and a synchronous
both these transmissions use bit synchronization
a synchronous transmission
when the clocks of the receiving and sending computers
are not synchronized
the form of transmission is referred to as a
synchronous transmission
when data is to be sent from one computer to another
it's broken up
into individual characters and sent in sequence
such transmission is called a synchronous transmission
when the receiving computer uses a clock
that's synchronized with the clock
of the sending computer
the clock establishes a rhythm
types of data transmission
audio data transmission
video data transmission
text document transmission
now we will learn about data manipulation
data manipulation is the process of taking data
and manipulating it in a method
making it easier to read organize
for example a log of data entries
could be organized in alphabetical order
making it easier to view and find information
data manipulation is
also often done with web server logs
to allow a website owner
to view their most popular pages and traffic sources
data manipulation language or DML
data manipulation language
DML is a structured computer language
used in databases to manipulate the data in some way
a few of the basic manipulations used in
data manipulation language
include adding to the database
changing a record
deleting a record
and moving data from one position to another
there are two types to data manipulation language
procedural
the procedural way of
coding is often used in business settings
and is the proper way of coding
the DML request
non procedural
in non procedural data manipulation language
the user
only tells the database what datum to work with
but not how to retrieve it
now we will study the academic perspectives
in recent years there has been tremendous
progress in the area of it
this has changed our day to day activities forever
it has become a vital tool in modern society
and one has reached the point where societies
not having access to it
are at a disadvantage
nations that come to the forefront and ITV Arena
have enormous economic benefits
in accessing information
the internet has become the number one source
year end 1998 statistics indicated
that more than 147 million people worldwide
were accessing the internet at least once a week
from home or office
the number of internet users was projected
to grow to approximately
320 million by 2000
and to 720 million by 2005
the traffic on the internet
will double approximately every 100 days
this rapid growth in internet traffic is
generating a high demand
for both hardware and software products
as well as for skilled it workers to improve
implement and manage various systems
let's now take a look
at commercial and employment perspective
in the modern world
acquisition of
computer skills is becoming necessary for employment
educational development and leisure
computer studies intend to furnish students with a
broad knowledge
of the nature of information processing
and how information and technology is used today
parallel to the rapid development
of information technology
is the uprising
of certain ethical and professional issues
as well as social implications
that were not thought of decades back
the internet particularly made a big impact not
only on the way
people around the globe communicate
but also it opened a wide door to information
changes brought about by information technology
are in the way one lives
perceives and does business
the computer is the target and the tool
for the perpetration of crime
it is used for the communication
of the criminal activity
such as the injection of a virus or worm
which can crash entire networks
now we will study ethical perspectives
some say that ethics has to do with religion
conversely ethics should not be confined with it
most religions advocate higher ethical standards
and yet if ethics were confined to religion
then ethics would apply only to religious people
some say that ethics is something about law
however there are some unethical acts
that are not covered by law
however conforming to the law
is absolutely considered as ethical
furthermore some say to be ethical
is to do what the society accepts
but the society can be morally corrupt
in this sense
ethics is not
generally related to the norms of the society
information technology has come a long way since then
and became a part
of our daily routine of everyone's life
both in business and social living
it has drastically developed over the past decades
and is still developing fast
the generation of computers become
smaller with greater speed and capability
as generations pass
now in the end
let us sunrise what we have Learned in this lecture
in the 1960s and 70s
the term information technology or I t
was a little known phrase
that was used by those
who worked in places like bangs and hospitals
to describe the
processes they used to store information
the information that a computer has at any given time
is technically what data its central processing unit
or CPU can directly access
this information is called memory
and the components that store it
are considered primary storage
a database is a collection of information
that is organized so that it can easily be accessed
managed and updated
in one view databases can be classified
according to types of content
bibliographic
full text numeric and images
queering is the capability to retrieve data
usually a data subset
based on some user defined formula
these data subsets are often referred to
as logical views
data transmission refers to the movement of data
in the form of
bits between two or more digital devices
this transfer of data takes place via some
form of transmission media